b'Version January 14, 2026\nPreprint typeset using L ATEX style openjournal v. 09/06/15\nBLIND DECONVOLUTION IN ASTRONOMY: HOW DOES A STANDALONE U-NET PERFORM?\nJean-Eric Campagne\nUniversit\xc2\xb4 e Paris-Saclay, CNRS/IN2P3, IJCLab, 91405 Orsay, France\nVersion January 14, 2026\nAbstract\nAims: This study investigates whether a U-Net architecture can perform standalone end-to-end\nblind deconvolution of astronomical images without any prior knowledge of the Point Spread Function\n(PSF) or noise characteristics. Our goal is to evaluate its performance against the number of training\nimages, classical Tikhonov deconvolution and to assess its generalization capability under varying\nseeing conditions and noise levels.\nMethods: Realistic astronomical observations are simulated using the GalSim toolkit, incorporat-\ning random transformations, PSF convolution (accounting for both optical and atmospheric effects),\nand Gaussian white noise. A U-Net model is trained using a Mean Square Error (MSE) loss function\non datasets of varying sizes, up to 40,000 images of size 48 \xc3\x97 48 from the COSMOS Real Galaxy\nDataset. Performance is evaluated using PSNR, SSIM, and cosine similarity metrics, with the latter\nemployed in a two-model framework to assess solution stability.\nResults: The U-Net model demonstrates effectiveness in blind deconvolution, with performance\nimproving consistently as the training dataset size increases, saturating beyond 5,000 images. Cosine\nsimilarity analysis reveals convergence between independently trained models, indicating stable solu-\ntions. Remarkably, the U-Net outperforms the oracle-like Tikhonov method in challenging conditions\n(low PSNR/medium SSIM). The model also generalizes well to unseen seeing and noise conditions,\nalthough optimal performance is achieved when training parameters include validation conditions.\nExperiments on synthetic C \xce\xb1 images further support the hypothesis that the U-Net learns a geometry-\nadaptive harmonic basis, akin to sparse representations observed in denoising tasks. These results\nalign with recent mathematical insights into its adaptive learning capabilities.\nSubject headings: Deconvolution, U-Net\n1. INTRODUCTION\nThe convolution operation and additive noise corrup-\ntion are ubiquitous in signal and image processing. In\nthis work, we focus on the latter context, where one ob-\nserves xo (an n \xc3\x97 n pixel image) as a 2D matrix resulting\nfrom the underlying ground true signal xt, first modi-\nfied by a convolution operator (or kernel) k and then\ncorrupted by additive noise n. This process can be ex-\npressed as:\nxo = k \xe2\x88\x97 xt + n, (1)\nwhere \xe2\x88\x97 denotes the convolution operation. If K (an\nn2\xc3\x97n2 matrix) represents the circulant matrix associated\nwith the convolution operator, the above equation can be\nreformulated using matrix-vector multiplication:\nxo = K\xc2\xafxt + n, (2)\nwhere \xc2\xafxt is a column vector obtained by stacking the el-\nements of the 2D matrix xt. For notational simplicity,\nwe will hereafter use xt, without explicitly mentioning\nthe context. Regarding n, we assume an additive i.i.d.\nwhite Gaussian noise, which for instance can model sen-\nsor noise during recording.\nIn astronomical image processing, which is the focus\nof this work, the convolution kernel\xe2\x80\x94known as the Point\njean-eric.campagne@ijclab.in2p3.fr\nSpread Function (PSF)\xe2\x80\x94arises from the optical transfer\nfunction of the telescope and atmospheric perturbations\nfor ground-based instruments. The PSF can vary across\nthe image itself for large field-of-view telescopes and may\nalso be wavelength-dependent, which is particularly chal-\nlenging when dispersing a spectrum in astronomical spec-\ntroscopy. The size of the kernel k is a priori not con-\nstrained to match the size of xo. For example, motion\nblur is typically modeled by a small kernel, whereas PSF\nmodels are often larger. The range of pixel values in xo\ndepends on the application, e.g., R+ or [\xe2\x88\x921, 1].\nOrigal HST image\n HST PSF\n naive deconv.\n0.01\n0.00\n0.01\n0.02\n0.03\n0.04\n0.05\n0.06\n0.005\n0.010\n0.015\n0.020\n0.025\n0.030\n0.035\n0.040\n0.4\n0.3\n0.2\n0.1\n0.0\n0.1\n0.2\n0.3\n0.4\nFig. 1.\xe2\x80\x94 Example of a naive deconvolution of HST image using\nthe associated HST PSF.\nThe inverse problem, known as deconvolution, has\nbeen addressed across various fields. It has evolved from\nclassical mathematical methods\xe2\x80\x94such as those devel-\noped by Norbert Wiener during World War II\xe2\x80\x94to mod-\narXiv:2601.08666v1  [astro-ph.IM]  13 Jan 2026\n2\nern deep learning-based approaches. If the kernel is a\nDirac delta function, the convolution operation vanishes,\nand the problem reduces to denoising. When neither the\nkernel (or PSF) nor the noise characteristics are known\na priori , the task is referred to as blind deconvolution, a\nwell-known ill-posed problem due to the infinite number\nof possible ( xt, k) pairs that yield the same convolution\nresult: e.g. ( xt, k) and (k\xe2\x88\x97xt, \xce\xb4) with \xce\xb4 the unit impulse.\nEven when the kernel is known ( non-blind case), naive\ndeconvolution is inadequate. Using F as the Fourier\ntransform, an estimate of the signal, noted \xcb\x86x, may be\nevaluated as1:\nF {\xcb\x86x} = F {xo}\nF {k} = F {xt} + F {n}\nF {k} (3)\nThe second term in the right-hand side of the second\nequality in Equation 3 reveals the dramatic amplifica-\ntion of the noise, overwhelming the signal. This oc-\ncurs because the Fourier spectrum of the kernel F {k}\nis concentrated at low frequencies (below a certain cut-\noff frequency), while the white Gaussian noise F {n} ex-\nhibits a constant power spectral density across all fre-\nquencies. Consequently, dividing by F {k} dispropor-\ntionately amplifies the noise at high frequencies, where\nF {k} approaches zero, leading to a reconstructed signal\ndominated by noise. An example of this noise enhance-\nment by a naive deconvolution is displayed in Figure 1.\nTechniques are therefore required to mitigate these issues\nboth in non-blind and blind deconvolution.\n1.1. Core Question: U-Net as an End-to-End Blind\nDeconvolution Network?\nThe U-Net architecture, originally introduced by Ron-\nneberger et al. (2015) for segmentation tasks, has\nemerged as a powerful tool in image processing, par-\nticularly as a denoiser. Its mathematical properties\nhave been studied in detail by Kadkhodaie et al. (2024),\nwho characterized what the network learns as a form\nof geometry-adaptive harmonic basis \xe2\x80\x94extending beyond\ntraditional steerable wavelet bases. Moreover, in the con-\ntext of diffusion generative models, where the denoiser\nplays a central role, the authors demonstrated a transi-\ntion from memorization to generalization as the dataset\nsize increases. These insights naturally lead to a critical\nquestion: Can such a network go beyond denoising and\nperform end-to-end blind deconvolution?\nWhile U-Net-based networks have been widely adopted\nas post-processing components in hybrid pipelines (e.g.,\ncombined with Tikhonov deconvolution or ADMM, see\nSection 3), we raise three key questions: (1) Can this ar-\nchitecture perform end-to-end blind deconvolution? (2)\nDoes it match the effectiveness of classical methods, such\nas the Tikhonov functional for which the kernel and noise\nlevel are provided? (3) How does dataset size impact\nits performance, keeping in mind the memorization-to-\ngeneralization transition?\nThis paper aims to address these questions through nu-\nmerical experiments, evaluating the U-Net\xe2\x80\x99s capacity to\n1 As a matter of definitiveness, the estimated signal is obtained\nvia \xcb\x86x = F \xe2\x88\x921{F {\xcb\x86x}} using the inverse Fourier transform. To avoid\nheavy notation, we have omitted the arguments of the functions:\ni.e. in the Fourier space F {x} is a function of \xcf\x89 = (\xcf\x891, \xcf\x892) for 2D\nspectrum, and in real space x is function of u = (u1, u2).\ngeneralize and adapt to the challenges of deconvolution.\nTo this end, the remainder of this paper is organized as\nfollows: Section 2 reviews the classical framework for de-\nconvolution, Section 3 discusses related works, Section 4\ndescribes the experimental setup, Section 5 presents the\nresults, and Section 6 concludes with a summary and\ndiscussion.\n2. BACKGOUND IN THE CONTEXT OF CLASSICAL\nFRAMEWORK\nThis section provides a brief overview of the mathe-\nmatical background for deconvolution, focusing on key\nconcepts and classical methods. It is not intended as an\nexhaustive analysis but rather as a concise introduction\nto the problem and its regularization techniques. For a\nmore in-depth treatment, readers may refer for insatnce\nto Chapter 13 of Mallat (2009).\nStarting with the non- blind deconvolution inverse\nproblem in a classical analysis framework and using ma-\ntrix notation, the solution to the naive deconvolution\n(Equation. 3) can be viewed as the solution to the fol-\nlowing least-squares problem:\n\xcb\x86xnaive = arg min\nx\n\xe2\x88\xa5xo \xe2\x88\x92 Kx\xe2\x88\xa52\n2 = K\xe2\x88\x921xo. (4)\nHowever, as discussed in the introduction, this approach\noften results in a significant amplification of noise.\nTo mitigate this issue, regularization techniques\xe2\x80\x94first\nintroduced by Tikhonov (1963)\xe2\x80\x94are studied in classical\ntext books (e.g., Mallat 2009) and in the context of as-\ntronomy in the review by Starck et al. (2002). These\ntechniques incorporate prior knowledge about the origi-\nnal signal, such as its expected smoothness. The least-\nsquares problem is then reformulated as the minimization\nof the Tikhonov quadratic functional as\n\xcb\x86x = arg min\nx\n\x1a1\n2 \xe2\x88\xa5xo \xe2\x88\x92 Kx\xe2\x88\xa52\n2 + \xce\xbb\xe2\x88\xa5Oxx\xe2\x88\xa52\n2\n\x1b\n, (5)\nwhere the first term ensures data fidelity, and the sec-\nond term acts as a regularizer on x, with its strength\ncontrolled by the parameter \xce\xbb \xe2\x88\x88 R+. This yields the\nfollowing solution2:\n\xcb\x86x = D\xcb\x86xnaive with D = (K\xe2\x88\x97K + \xce\xbbO\xe2\x88\x97\nxOx)\xe2\x88\x921 K\xe2\x88\x97K.\n(6)\nThe operator D is recognized as a linear denoiser (Mal-\nlat 2009), reducing amplified noise with a regularization\nstrength controlled by the parameter \xce\xbb.\nIn the Fourier domain, this formulation becomes:\nF {\xcb\x86x} = F {k}\xe2\x88\x97\n|F {k}|2 + \xce\xbb|F {ox}|2 \xc3\x97 F {xo}, (7)\nwhere the regularization term \xe2\x88\xa5Oxx\xe2\x88\xa52\n2 is replaced by\n\xe2\x88\xa5ox \xe2\x88\x97 x\xe2\x88\xa52\n2. This highlights the role of a filter g associ-\nated with a spectral window function Wox, such that:\n\xcb\x86x = g \xe2\x88\x97 xo \xe2\x87\x94 F { \xcb\x86x} = F {g}F {xo},\nwith F {g} := Wox\nF {k} . (8)\nStarck et al. (2002) outlines general properties that\nWox must satisfy to serve as an effective regularization\n2 In matrix notation A\xe2\x88\x97 denotes the conjugate transpose of A.\n3\nwindow. Common choices for the operator Ox are high-\npass filters such as the gradient and the Laplacian. With\nsuch filters, Wox approaches 1 at low frequencies and 0\nat high frequencies, effectively suppressing noise. The\nhyperparameter \xce\xbb acts as a trade-off between these two\nregimes: increasing \xce\xbb enhances the regularity of the so-\nlution \xcb\x86x. Alternative window functions are also possible,\nsuch as a Gaussian form W (\xcf\x89) = e\xe2\x88\x92\xce\xb1\xe2\x88\xa5\xcf\x89\xe2\x88\xa52\n.\nIn the same spirit, the Wiener deconvolution leads to\nthe following spectral window:\nW Wiener = |F {k}|2\n|F {k}|2 + S{n}/S{xt} , (9)\nwhere S{n} and S{xt} represent the power spectral den-\nsities of the noise and the ground truth signal, respec-\ntively. The second term in the denominator corresponds\nto the inverse signal-to-noise ratio in Fourier space, which\ntends to zero at low frequencies and infinity at high fre-\nquencies. While this satisfies the conditions for a good\nwindow, it is more akin to an oracle, as it requires a pri-\nori knowledge of the noise and true image power spectra.\nSome limitations of Tikhonov quadratic regulariza-\ntion are highlighted in Mallat (2009); Sureau et al.\n(2020). Specifically, when the ground truth signal xt\nis non-smooth\xe2\x80\x94such as in cases involving rapid con-\ntrast transitions\xe2\x80\x94the denoising operator, by suppress-\ning small-scale details, may introduce significant errors.\nAdditionally, the derivative operator Ox relies on global\nsignal properties, failing to capture local characteristics.\nTo address these issues, it has been proposed to replace\nEquation 5 with the following formulation:\n\xcb\x86x = arg min\nx\n\x1a1\n2 \xe2\x88\xa5xo \xe2\x88\x92 k \xe2\x88\x97 x\xe2\x88\xa52\n2 + \xce\xbb\xe2\x88\xa5os\nx \xe2\x88\x97 x\xe2\x88\xa51\n\x1b\n, (10)\nHere, the operator os\nx is carefully chosen to promote a\nsparse representation of the ground truth signal, as dis-\ncussed in Mallat (2009). This can be achieved through\nmultiresolution analysis using the wavelet transform.\nFurthermore, the L1-norm in the regularization term is\nemployed to enforce solution sparsity.\nBlind deconvolution can be seen as an extension of the\nabove problem. For instance, one may use the following\ngeneralized objective function:\nL(x, k) = \xe2\x84\x93(xo, k \xe2\x88\x97 x) + \xce\xbbx Rx(x) + \xce\xbbk Rk(k), (11)\nwhere \xe2\x84\x93 is a loss function accounting for the data fidelity\nterm, and Rx (resp. Rk) denotes the regularizer for x\n(resp. k). Zhuang et al. (2023) discuss some choices for\nthese key elements.\nTurning to neural networks blind deconvolution of as-\ntronomical images mostly leads to hybrid solutions where\nthe network acts as a denoiser, as mentioned in the fol-\nlowing Section 3, while we ask for end-to-end realisation.\n3. SOME RELATED WORKS\nAs a preliminary note, the number of articles address-\ning the deconvolution task may exceed ten thousand over\nthe past decade3. This reflects the broad applicability of\n3 This rough estimate is based on an AI-assisted bibliometric\nsearch (e.g., using tools such as https://scispace.com/).\nimage deconvolution across diverse fields, including mi-\ncroscopy, medical imaging, photography, video process-\ning, computer vision, archival restoration, and remote\nsensing. Given the vast scope of the subject, the follow-\ning discussion does not claim to represent its full diver-\nsity. Instead, we categorize methods based on whether\nthey employ neural networks. While our work, presented\nin Section 4, relies exclusively on deep networks, we ac-\nknowledge the relevance of classical analysis approaches.\n3.1. Non-Neural Network Techniques\nWe mention the review by Satish et al. (2020) that\nexplores different methods, notably improvements up on\nMaximum a Posteriori Estimation for blind deconvolu-\ntion, focusing in the context of non-astronomical images.\nStarck et al. (2002) reviewed deconvolution methods ap-\nplied specifically in astronomy before the deep learning\nage, with a particular focus on multiresolution wavelet-\nbased transforms. In the exposed classical deconvolution\nmethods, the PSF is assumed to be known, and one of\nthe methods, i.e. Tikhonov regularisation is described in\nSection 2.\nMore recently, advances have been made to address\nthe challenges of deconvolution in dynamic or complex\nobservational conditions. Millon et al. (2024) introduced\nSTARRED, a method performing joint deconvolution of\nall the images in a time series, accounting for epoch-to-\nepoch variations of the PSF due to atmospheric condi-\ntions. The goal is to extract light curves of variable or\ntransient point sources (e.g., stars, supernovae, lensed\nquasars) while reconstructing the underlying extended\nscene (galaxies, host galaxies). The method is based on\nthe principles of MCF (Magain et al. 1998) and Firedec\n(Cantale et al. 2016), paying attention to the Nyquist-\nShannon sampling theorem in choosing the PSF model-\ning. In parallel, Berdeu (2024) proposed a blind deconvo-\nlution technique tailored for adaptive optics images. This\nmethod estimates both the PSF (including halo) and the\nsharp object image without prior knowledge, alternating\nbetween PSF core estimation, halo modeling, and de-\nconvolution. The result is improved sharpness and the\nability to reveal faint companions, all without relying on\ndeep learning but instead exploiting the sharp features\nof Solar System objects.\n3.2. Neural Network Techniques\nConcerning non-astronomical domains, the reader can\nbenefit from Singhal et al. (2025)\xe2\x80\x99s review, as well as\nspecific works such as Jin et al. (2017) in the context of\nmedical imaging and Schuler et al. (2016); Kupyn et al.\n(2019); Cho et al. (2021); Zhuang et al. (2023); Guo et al.\n(2025) designed for blur on natural images (e.g. long ex-\nposures inducing camera shake) or otherwise degraded\nimages, often assuming simple convolutional kernels and\nnoise models. In contrast, astronomical imaging involves\ncomplex, generally spatially-varying PSFs (e.g., due to\noptics and atmospheric turbulence), making direct ap-\nplication of these methods unsuitable without adapting\nthe physical models and constraints. It is worth notic-\ning that early usages of neural networks can be found\nfor non- blind in Xu et al. (2014) and for blind decon-\nvolution in Schuler et al. (2016). Xu et al. (2014) had\nused a shallow 2-hidden layers network. Schuler et al.\n4\n(2016) proceeded to first a feature extraction thanks to\na convolutional layer, second a kernel estimation module\nand finally a image restoration module. These simple\narchitectures reflect the early use of neural networks for\ndeconvolution, which has since evolved significantly in\nmodern works.\nSureau et al. (2020) used a U-Net-based network,\nto address deconvolution for large surveys with space-\nvariant PSFs. Two strategies were explored: one per-\nforms a conventional deconvolution using a closed-form\nTikhonov solution, then applies the U-Net as a post-\nprocessing refinement (Tikhonet); the other uses an iter-\native deconvolution framework based on the Alternat-\ning Direction Method of Multipliers (ADMM), where\nthe neural network helps in the iterative reconstruction.\nBoth outperformed standard deconvolution but assumed\nthe PSF (or its local variant) was known beforehand.\nNammour et al. (2021); Nammour et al. (2022) had ex-\ntended the Tikhonet method using a shape constraint\nleading to the ShapeNet model.\nFollowing Sureau et al. (2020), Li and Alexander\n(2023) used a Plug-and-Play ADMM with a known PSF,\nwhere a neural network learns denoising priors and hy-\nperparameters from simulated galaxy images. It enables\nrobust deconvolution even with PSF errors but does not\nperform blind deconvolution.\nAkhaury et al. (2024) introduced a hybrid deconvolu-\ntion framework. The process proceeds in three steps: a\nclassical deconvolution (Tikhonov filter) using a known\nPSF, then denoising refinement with SUNet (a U-Net\nwith Swin Transformer blocks), and a third \xe2\x80\x9cdebiasing\xe2\x80\x9d\nstep based on a multi-resolution support in wavelet space\nto recover flux/fine structures that may have been lost or\nbiased by the neural network\xe2\x80\x99s output. Tested on HST\nand VLT images, it efficiently recovers fine structures but\ndoes not perform blind deconvolution.\n3.3. U-Net Inspired Model as Denoiser\nIt is noticeable that in many works, a modified U-Net\nis employed, and Table 1 summarizes the use of such\nnetworks in the deconvolution of galaxy images. How-\never, none of them use an end-to-end deconvolution net-\nwork. Instead, the U-Net serves as a denoiser, prior,\nor post-processing component in a hybrid pipeline that\ncombines classical or physics-based deconvolution (or it-\nerative optimization) with deep learning-based correc-\ntion or regularization. As Sureau et al. (2020) argue,\nthey modified the architecture (called XDense) (sepa-\nrable convolutions, dense blocks, average pooling, re-\nmoval of the global skip connection from input to out-\nput) to reduce the total number of parameters, pre-\nvent overfitting when data is limited, preserve faint\npixel information, improve performance on low signal-\nto-noise galaxy images, and make the network more\nsuitable for deconvolution (rather than segmentation).\nAkhaury et al. (2024) based their work on the SUNet\ndenoiser by Fan et al. (2022). The U-Net architecture\n(encoder/decoder + skip-connections) is globally kept,\nbut convolutional blocks are replaced by transformer-\nbased blocks (Swin Transformer) to better handle de-\nconvolution/restoration tasks. So the inductive bias\nchanges from locality/translation invariance in Convo-\nlutional Neural Networks (CNN) to self-attention-based\nfeature extraction with long-range relationships. Chang-\ning from CNNs to transformers increases architectural\ncomplexity and the number of parameters to train.\n4. EXPERIMENT SETUP\nAs described in Section 1.1, we aim to use a U-Net ar-\nchitecture to measure the standalone ability of the neural\nnetwork to perform an end-to-end blind deconvolution.\nFor the experimental setup, we have been inspired by Li\nand Alexander (2023), although our perspective is differ-\nent.\n4.1. U-Net architecture and training\nThe default U-Net architecture used contains 2 encoder\nand 2 decoder blocks, as well as a single mid-level block\n(Ronneberger et al. 2015). Each block consists of 2 con-\nvolutional layers followed by a ReLU non-linearity and\nbatch normalization. Each encoder block is followed by\na 2 \xc3\x97 2 spatial downsampling and a twofold increase in\nthe number of channels. Each decoder block is followed\nby a 2 \xc3\x97 2 spatial upsampling and a twofold reduction\nof channels. This leads to 1 .8m trainable parameters \xce\xb8.\nThis architecture is well-suited for processing images of\nthe sizes considered in the next section.\nThe objective function L(\xce\xb8) used during the train-\ning phase of the network D\xce\xb8 is the Mean Square Error\n(MSE)4. Our goal is to minimize this loss over a total of\nN primary images, defined as follows:\nL(\xce\xb8) = 1\nN\nNX\ni=1\n\xe2\x88\xa5xi,e\nt \xe2\x88\x92 D\xce\xb8(xi,e\no )\xe2\x88\xa52\n2, (12)\nwhere the index e spans the total number of epochs.\nHowever, rather than using static datasets that are\ntypically prepared once for training, testing, and vali-\ndation, the term image forward modelling (or simulator)\nis more appropriate 5. For clarity, consider the above ex-\npression with j denoting an instance of the couple ( i, e)\nsuch that\nxj\nt = Gt(zj) and xj\no = Gk(z\xe2\x80\xb2j) \xe2\x88\x97 xj\nt + Gn(z\xe2\x80\xb2\xe2\x80\xb2j), (13)\nwhere, in compact notation, Gt, Gk, and Gn represent\nthe generators for the new ground truth image, the new\nPSF, and the noise, respectively, with (zj, z\xe2\x80\xb2j, z\xe2\x80\xb2\xe2\x80\xb2j) being\nrandom vectors. This approach is inspired by Li and\nAlexander (2023), but with the key difference that the\npairs of simulated ground truth and observed images are\nnot fixed prior to the learning phase.\nThe network implementation and training/testing\nphases use the PyTorch6 framework (Paszke et al.\n2019). All experiments were conducted on a single\nNvidia V100-32g GPU at the Jean Zay supercomputer\nat IDRIS7, a national computing center for the France\xe2\x80\x99s\n4 We also tested a multi-scale version of the MSE loss, as pro-\nposed in Li and Alexander (2023). However, since the performance\nobtained with the multi-scale MSE was statistically indistinguish-\nable from that achieved with the standard MSE, we opted to retain\nthe MSE loss. This decision is further supported by Kadkhodaie\net al. (2024), which links the training of denoisers to the gradient of\nthe log-likelihood of the noisy image distribution (i.e., the score).\n5 This is an extension of data augmentation, which often uses\nrotation, translation, resizing, and cropping transformations.\n6 https://pytorch.org/\n7 http://www.idris.fr/eng/jean-zay/jean-zay-presentation-eng.\nhtml\n5\nTABLE 1\nUse of U-Net variants and their role in selected image deconvolution studies.\nReference U-Net Type Role of U-Net\nAkhaury et al. (2024) Swin-UNet Post-deconvolution denoising/correction/restoration,\ncombined with Tikhonov deconvolution and wavelet-\nbased debiasing.\nLi and Alexander (2023) ResUNet Denoising/regularization inside unrolled ADMM\ndeconvolution\nSureau et al. (2020) Modified U-Net Post-processing denoiser (Tikhonet) or denoiser-prior\nin iterative ADMM deconvolution (ADMMnet)\nNational Center for Scientific Research (CNRS). Train-\ning was carried out on batches of size 40 for 100 epochs,\nwhich was sufficient to achieve loss convergence, using\nthe Adam optimizer (Kingma and Ba 2015) with the\nReduceLROnPlateau learning rate scheduler. The initial\nlearning rate was set to 10\xe2\x88\x922, with (patience, factor,\nmin lr) parameter values of (5 , 0.5, 10\xe2\x88\x925).\n4.2. Image forward modelling\nWe used the facility offered by the galaxy image sim-\nulation toolkit GalSim (Rowe et al. 2015)8 to read and\nstore information about specific training samples of real-\nistic galaxies, such as the COSMOS Real Galaxy Dataset\n(Mandelbaum et al. 2012). We preferred real galaxy im-\nages over synthetic images, despite the limited dataset\nsizes. The Hubble Space Telescope (HST) images re-\ntained, each with at least 48 \xc3\x97 48 pixels, amount to\nabout 54 , 000, which makes feasible a study of the per-\nformance with respect to the training dataset size. Each\nHST galaxy image is loaded with its associated HST PSF\nimage and the correlated noise image. After HST PSF\nnormalization, the galsim.RealGalaxy class was used to\nproduce a galsim.GSObject, the key object of GalSim.\nIt is worth mentioning that a naive deconvolution takes\nplace at this stage 9.\nThe image generator follows a series of steps (see Ta-\nble 2 in Appendix A for the random distributions of\nthe parameters and their default values) before convolv-\ning the result with a new PSF. First, random trans-\nformations\xe2\x80\x94rotation, translation, shear, and magnifica-\ntion\xe2\x80\x94are applied to the image. The transformed image\nis then projected into an array of size fov \xc3\x97 upsampling,\nwhere fov represents the field of view of the new image\nin pixels (default: 48) and upsampling is the upsampling\nfactor (default: 4). Finally, the enlarged image is con-\nvolved using the HST PSF, simulating an observation by\nthe Hubble Space Telescope 10.\nUnlike Li and Alexander (2023), we chose to use the\nHST pixel scale of 0 .03 arcsec instead of an LSST-\ninspired value, as the GalSim drawing function would\notherwise result in a zero-padded image with only a\nsmall fraction of non-null pixel values 11. Finally, the\nimage pixel values are adjusted to the [ \xe2\x88\x921, 1] range. Al-\nthough this is not realistic for real astronomical images,\nit matches the Gaussian white noise setup used in our\ntests.\n8 https://github.com/GalSim-developers/GalSim\n9 Details are available in the GalSim documentation.\n10 See the note above regarding the default naive deconvolution\napproach.\n11 This is also why we only used rotation angles as integer mul-\ntiples of \xcf\x80/2, equivalent to horizontal or vertical flips.\nThe simulator then generates a new PSF, account-\ning for both optical and atmospheric aspects. For opti-\ncal characteristics, using the galsim.OpticalPSF func-\ntion, the generator randomly samples the following pa-\nrameters: (1) defocusing, to simulate deviations from\nthe ideal focal plane; (2) optical aberrations, including\nspherical aberration, biaxial astigmatism, coma, and tre-\nfoil, to model common imperfections in optical systems;\nand (3) obturation ratio and \xce\xbb/D, which determine the\ndiffraction-limited resolution and the overall PSF shape.\nAn example is shown in Figure 2 (more examples are\nprovided in Appendix B).\nlod 0.024\ndefocus -0.072\ncoma1 0.177\ncoma2 -0.027\nastig1 0.016\nastig2 0.005\nobs 0.111\nspher 0.056\ntref1 0.028\ntref2 0.001\nFig. 2.\xe2\x80\x94 Example of an optical PSF (zoom \xc3\x973) obtained from\ngalsim.OpticalPSF.\nFor atmospheric perturbations, we employ the Kol-\nmogorov surface brightness profile with a randomly sam-\npled seeing (FWHM) value ( galsim.Kolmogorov). A\nrandom shear is also applied to simulate atmospheric\nvariations that introduce shape noise. The final PSF\nis obtained by convolving both optical and atmospheric\ncontributions. Examples are shown in Figure 3. This\nNo atm.\n atm: 5. 10 2\natm: 2. 10 1\natm: 4. 10 1\nFig. 3.\xe2\x80\x94 Examples of effects of atmospheric seeing (the FWHM\nof Kolmogorov function is noted atm) on the optical PSF shown on\nFigure 3.\nmethodology ensures that the generated PSFs reflect\na diverse range of optical and atmospheric conditions,\nthereby enhancing the robustness of the deconvolution\nprocess under study.\nThe final steps of the generator apply non-overlapping\naverage pooling with a 4 \xc3\x97 4 kernel (matching the\nupsampling = 4 factor cited above), reducing the im-\nage to a spatial resolution of 48 \xc3\x97 48 pixels (default).\nSubsequently, additive i.i.d. Gaussian white noise is in-\n6\njected with a standard deviation uniformly sampled from\nthe interval [0, 1]. This noise generation method follows\nCampagne (2025) and contrasts with Li and Alexander\n(2023), who use a fixed standard deviation inspired by\nLSST electronic readout noise 12.\n5. EXPERIMENT RESULTS\nIn the following, we present results obtained after\ntraining U-Net models as described in Section 4.1. All\nfigures are generated from Python notebooks available in\nthe companion GitHub repository (Section 7). As a re-\nminder, unless otherwise specified, the default maximal\nvalues for the Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) of\nthe Kolmogorov function (representing the seeing) and\nthe standard deviation of the Gaussian white noise are\nset to 0 .4 and 1 .0, respectively. The default training\ndataset consists of 40 , 000 images, selected from a total\nof approximately 54, 000 available images. An additional\n1, 000 images, generated using the same forward mod-\nelling process described in Section 4.2, are reserved exclu-\nsively for the validation dataset. Importantly, these vali-\ndation images were never used during any model training\nphase.\n5.1. Galaxy image U-Net deconvolutions: some\nillustrations\nAfter setting a series of parameters\xe2\x80\x94first to define the\noptical PSF properties and second to modify the original\nHST galaxy image\xe2\x80\x94we can then simulate varying seeing\nand noise conditions. This process enables us to generate\na set of observed images from a ground truth reference,\nwhich are subsequently processed using the same U-Net\nmodel for deconvolution. Figure 4 provides illustrative\nexamples of this workflow.\nThe two small images on the left show the ground truth\n(48 \xc3\x97 48 pixels) and a \xc3\x976 zoom of a 32 \xc3\x97 32 pixel patch\nextracted from the optical PSF, which is 192\xc3\x97192 pixels.\nThe 4 \xc3\x97 8 grid of 48 \xc3\x97 48 pixel images is divided into two\n4 \xc3\x97 4 sub-grids:\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Left grid ( \xe2\x80\x9cConvoluted and noisy\xe2\x80\x9d ): Each image\ncorresponds to a specific combination of seeing con-\nditions (atmospheric perturbation factor, \xe2\x80\x9catm\xe2\x80\x9d,\nranging from 10 \xe2\x88\x924\xe2\x80\x94no perturbation\xe2\x80\x94to 0 .4, the\nmaximum value used during U-Net training) and\nnoise levels (standard deviation, \xe2\x80\x9cnoise\xe2\x80\x9d, ranging\nfrom 0\xe2\x80\x94no added noise\xe2\x80\x94to 1 .0, the maximum\nvalue used during training).\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Right grid ( \xe2\x80\x9cDeconvoluted\xe2\x80\x9d): The correspond-\ning deconvoluted images, processed by the U-Net\nmodel.\nFor each image ( img) in both grids, we computed the\nPeak Signal-to-Noise Ratio (PSNR) using the Mean\nSquared Error (MSE) metric, with the ground truth im-\nage (ref) as reference 13:\nPSNR(img, ref) = \xe2\x88\x9210 log10 (MSE(img, ref)) . (14)\n12 LSST stands for Legacy Survey of Space and Time, al-\nthough this acronym is more commonly used to refer to the\nsurvey performed by the Simonyi Survey Telescope at the Vera\nC. Rubin Observatory, equipped with the LSST Camera. See\nhttps://rubinobservatory.org/ for more information.\n13 As a reminder, the pixel values of the ground truth image are\nin the range [ \xe2\x88\x921, 1].\nWhile the PSNR is typically used for noisy images\xe2\x80\x94\nwhere it simplifies to \xe2\x88\x9220 log10 \xcf\x83 for additive Gaussian\nnoise with standard deviation \xcf\x83\xe2\x80\x94we adopt the PSNR\nnotation here as a convenient expression of the MSE in\ndecibels (dB).\nEach pair of images\xe2\x80\x94one from the left grid ( \xe2\x80\x9cCon-\nvoluted and noisy\xe2\x80\x9d ) and its corresponding deconvoluted\nimage from the right grid\xe2\x80\x94can be directly compared,\nboth visually and through the quoted PSNR values, to\nassess the model\xe2\x80\x99s performance under varying degrada-\ntion conditions. One can observe the following:\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Left grid ( \xe2\x80\x9cConvoluted and noisy\xe2\x80\x9d ): The images\nbecome progressively blurrier and noisier as theatm\nand noise parameters increase. The PSNR values,\nshown at the top of each image, decrease with in-\ncreasing noise and atmospheric perturbations, as\nexpected due to the degradation of image quality\ncaused by noise and convolution.\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Right grid ( \xe2\x80\x9cDeconvoluted\xe2\x80\x9d): The deconvoluted\nimages exhibit significant improvement compared\nto the noisy images. Their PSNR values are sub-\nstantially higher than those of their corresponding\nconvoluted and noisy counterparts, clearly indicat-\ning a superior reconstruction quality. Even under\nhigh noise and perturbation conditions, the U-Net\nmodel successfully restores images, although the\nquality slightly degrades with increasing perturba-\ntions.\nThese first results indicate the ability of the U-Net model\nto deconvolve galaxy images degraded by noise and at-\nmospheric perturbations. The visual results and PSNR\nvalues show that the model is robust even under chal-\nlenging conditions, although the quality of the decon-\nvolution slightly decreases with increasing perturbations\nand noise.\nIn the following, we extend our analysis beyond these\ninitial results, which were obtained using a single ground\ntruth image and evaluated through visual inspection and\nPSNR metrics.\n5.2. Performance evaluation using PSNR and SSIM\nmetrics: impact of training set size\nWe now assess the model\xe2\x80\x99s performance on a valida-\ntion set of 1000 images. Besides the PSNR metric, we\nalso use the Structural Similarity Index (SSIM) 14\xe2\x80\x93even\nif introduced first by Wang et al. (2004) in the context\nof natural images\xe2\x80\x93 which provides a number in the range\n[0, 1] comparing the structural information or spatial in-\nterdependencies: the higher is the index value, higher is\nthe similarity between two images. Furthermore, we in-\nvestigate the impact of varying the number of training\nimages from 100 up to 40 , 000.\nThe results are presented in Figure 5. The left sub-\nfigure shows the PSNR of the U-Net deconvolved im-\nages as a function of the PSNR of the observed images,\nwhile the right subfigure illustrates the same relation-\nship for the SSIM metric. In both subfigures, the color\ngradient of the data points\xe2\x80\x94ranging from light blue to\n14 We have used the structural similarity function of the\nscikit-image library.\n7\nground truth\nPSF optics\nzoom:6.00\nnoise:0.000\n25.67\natm: 1. 10 4\n24.65\natm: 5. 10 2\n19.11\natm: 2. 10 1\n14.39\natm: 4. 10 1\n28.6\n 28.5\n 26.5\n 22.0\nnoise:0.100\n18.83\n 18.63\n 16.46\n 13.39\n 27.5\n 27.6\n 25.0\n 21.8\nnoise:0.500\n5.79\n 6.05\n 5.93\n 5.45\n 24.5\n 23.3\n 22.3\n 19.2\nnoise:1.000\n0.04\n -0.07\n 0.01\n 0.11\n 20.3\n 23.0\n 19.5\n 16.6\nConvoluted and noisy Deconvoluted\nFig. 4.\xe2\x80\x94 Examples of U-Net deconvolution (see text).\n0 5 10 15 20 25 30 35\nPSNR obs. (dB)\n0\n5\n10\n15\n20\n25\n30\n35PSNR deconv. (db)\nN=100\nN=500\nN=1000\nN=5000\nN=10000\nN=20000\nN=40000\n0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0\nSSIM obs.\n0.0\n0.2\n0.4\n0.6\n0.8\n1.0SSIM deconv.\nN=100\nN=500\nN=1000\nN=5000\nN=10000\nN=20000\nN=40000\nFig. 5.\xe2\x80\x94 Left: PSNR of deconvolved images as a function of the PSNR of the observed images. The color gradient of the data points,\nranging from light blue to black, distinguishes U-Net models trained with increasing sizes of the training dataset ( N = 100, N = 500,\nN = 1000, N = 5000, N = 10000, N = 20000, and N = 40000). The error bars represent the standard error on the mean in each bin of\nthe profile histogram. Right: same legend but considering the SSIM metric. In each subfigure, the dashed line represents the case where\nthe PSNR (or SSIM) of the deconvolved images is equal to the PSNR (or SSIM) of the observed images.\nblack\xe2\x80\x94represents U-Net models trained with increasing\ntraining dataset sizes (see figure caption for specific val-\nues). The error bars indicate the standard error on the\nmean for each bin of the profile histogram.\nFirst, let us consider the case where the U-Net model\nhas been trained with N = 40, 000 images, as discussed\nin the previous section. The corresponding data points,\nrepresented by black dots, are all positioned above the\ndiagonal dashed line. This indicates that the U-Net con-\nsistently achieves an improvement in image restoration,\nparticularly for observed images with low PSNR and\nSSIM values. This trend underscores the model\xe2\x80\x99s effec-\ntiveness in enhancing image quality even under challeng-\ning conditions.\nSecondly, the quality of image restoration clearly im-\nproves with the number of training images, reaching\nnear-optimal performance for N > 5, 000. This high-\nlights the need for a sufficiently large training set to fully\nexploit the model\xe2\x80\x99s capabilities, a point further elabo-\nrated in the next section through cosine similarity anal-\nysis.\n5.3. The Cosine Similarity: Comparison of Two U-Net\nModels\nThe previous section suggests that, with N > 5, 000\ntraining images, the PSNR and SSIM performances tend\nto saturate. However, one may question whether this\nsaturation behavior persists when comparing the outputs\nof two independently trained U-Net models. Specifically,\nwe address the following question: Do two U-Net models,\ntrained with two disjoint training sets of the same size,\nproduce similar restored images from the same observed\nimage? This question is inspired by our previous analysis\nin the context of galaxy image generation (Campagne\n2025).\nTo investigate this, we examine the cosine similarity\nbetween the outputs of two U-Net models, denoted as\nunet1 and unet2. For this purpose, the 40 , 000 train-\ning images are split into pairs of disjoint subsets ( S1,\nS2) of equal size, ranging from 100 to 20 , 000 images, to\nindependently train unet1 and unet2. The results are\npresented in Figure 6.\nThe first two rows display the cosine similarity distri-\n8\n0.96 0.98 1.00\n100\n101\n102\nCounts\nN train=100\nunet 1 vs unet 2 (all)\ngt vs gt (zoom)\n0.96 0.98 1.00\n100\n101\n102\nN train=500\n0.96 0.98 1.00\n100\n101\n102\nN train=1000\n0.96 0.98 1.00\ncosine\n100\n101\n102\nCounts\nN train=5000\n0.96 0.98 1.00\ncosine\n100\n101\n102\nN train=10000\n0.96 0.98 1.00\ncosine\n100\n101\n102\nN train=20000\n0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1.0\ncosine\n100\n101\nCounts\ngt vs gt (all)\ngt vs gt (zoom)\nFig. 6.\xe2\x80\x94 Cosine similarity distributions for two U-Net models trained with varying dataset sizes. The blue histograms represent the\ncosine similarity between the outputs of unet1 and unet2, while the orange histograms show the maximum cosine similarity between two\nground truth images.\nbutions (blue histograms) for U-Net models trained with\nincreasing dataset sizes. These blue histograms are de-\nrived from the 1, 000 validation images. For comparison,\nthe distributions of the maximum cosine similarity be-\ntween two ground truth images are also shown (orange\nhistograms, labeled \xe2\x80\x9dzoom\xe2\x80\x9d).\nIn the last row, we present the distribution of the\nmaximum cosine similarity for all ground truth images\n(blue histogram), with an overlay zooming into the range\n[0.95, 1.0], as used in the first two rows.\nAs the training set size increases, a peak in the cosine\nsimilarity blue histograms emerges and moves closer to\nthe maximal value (i.e., 1), indicating that the outputs of\nthe two U-Net models become increasingly similar. No-\ntably, the histogram obtained with only the ground truth\nimages (orange) does not exhibit such a peak, indicating\nthat there are no pairs of highly similar ground truth\nimages. Even beyond N = 5 , 000, the cosine similar-\nity continues to increase when considering N = 20, 000.\nTherefore, we anticipate that with N = 40, 000, the simi-\nlarity would be even higher, although we cannot test this\nin practice due to the limited number of available ground\ntruth images. Additionally, this numerical experiment\nreinforces the extra confidence in U-Net outputs using\nthe two-models framework.\n5.4. U-Net Blind Deconvolution versus Tikhonov\nNon-Blind Deconvolution\nAs demonstrated in the previous sections, the end-to-\nend blind deconvolution performed by the U-Net model\nproves to be highly effective when trained with a suffi-\ncient number of images. In Section 2, we introduced the\nTikhonov functional (Equation 5) in the context of non-\nblind deconvolution. Despite its inherent limitations, we\nemploy the Tikhonov approach as an oracle-like com-\nparator, leveraging perfect knowledge of both the true\nPSF and the ground truth images. This allows us to es-\ntablish a reference for evaluating the blind deconvolution\nperformance of the U-Net model.\nTo implement this comparison, we use the Laplacian as\nthe regularization operator and leverage the image gen-\neration process described in Equation 13 and Section 4.2.\nThe true PSF is provided 15 as input to compute the de-\nconvolved image using Equation 6. The hyperparameter\n\xce\xbb is optimized to maximize PSNR between the ground\ntruth and the deconvolved images.\nThe results using the U-Net models trained with vari-\nable training set sizes, as described in Section 5.2, are\npresented in Figure 7. The left subfigure compares the\nPSNR metric, while the right subfigure compares the\nSSIM metric, both between the U-Net blind deconvo-\nlution and the Tikhonov non-blind deconvolution.\nThe results confirm that the U-Net blind deconvolu-\ntion performance improves consistently with an increas-\ning number of training images, in line with the conclu-\nsions presented in Sections 5.2 and 5.3. Notably, when\ntrained with 40, 000 images (black dots), the U-Net blind\n15 Note that the computations are performed in the Fourier\nspace.\n9\n5 10 15 20 25 30 35 40\nPSNR Tikhonov (dB)\n5\n10\n15\n20\n25\n30\n35\n40PSNR deconv. (db)\nN=100\nN=500\nN=1000\nN=5000\nN=10000\nN=20000\nN=40000\n0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0\nSSIM Tikhonov\n0.0\n0.2\n0.4\n0.6\n0.8\n1.0SSIM Unet\nN=100\nN=500\nN=1000\nN=5000\nN=10000\nN=20000\nN=40000\nFig. 7.\xe2\x80\x94 Left: PSNR comparison between U-Net blind deconvolution and Tikhonov non-blind deconvolution for different training set\nsizes. The horizontal axis represents the PSNR of the Tikhonov output with respect to the ground truth, while the vertical axis represents\nthe PSNR of the U-Net output. The legend indicates the number of training images used for the U-Net model. Right: same legend but\nconsidering the SSIM metric. In each subfigure, the dashed line represents the case where the PSNR (or SSIM) of the deconvolved images\nis equal to the PSNR (or SSIM) of the Tikhonov deconvolved images.\ndeconvolution not only achieves performance levels com-\nparable to the non-blind oracle-like Tikhonov deconvo-\nlution but also significantly outperforms it in challeng-\ning conditions, specifically at low PSNR and medium\nSSIM values. This unexpected outcome underscores the\nrobustness of the U-Net blind deconvolution approach\nwhen trained using the methodology described in Sec-\ntions 4.1 and 4.2.\n5.5. Generalization: Seeing and Noise Standard\nDeviation\nIn the previous sections, all datasets\xe2\x80\x94training, test-\ning, and and validation\xe2\x80\x94were generated (as described\nin Section 4.2) using default maximal values for the Full\nWidth at Half Maximum (FWHM) of the Kolmogorov\nfunction (representing the seeing) and the standard de-\nviation of the Gaussian white noise. As a reminder,\nthese values were set to atmos fwhm max = 0 .4 and\nsigma noise max = 1.0, respectively (see Table 2).\nIn this section, we investigate the generalization capa-\nbility of a trained U-Net model under two distinct sce-\nnarios:\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Varying the atmospheric seeing: In this scenario,\nwe evaluate the performance of U-Net models\ntrained with the default sigma noise max = 1 .0\nand variable atmos fwhm max values ranging from\n0.1 to 0 .8. The models are then applied to valida-\ntion images generated with atmos fwhm max = 0.8\nand the default sigma noise max = 1.0.\nThe left plot of Figure 8 shows that the SSIM of\nthe deconvolved images is relatively stable with re-\nspect to the maximum FWHM value used during\ntraining. However, models trained with FWHM\nvalues closer to those of the validation images (e.g.,\natmos fwhm max = 0.8, shown in red) achieve sig-\nnificantly better performances.\n\xe2\x80\xa2 Varying the noise level: In this scenario, we evalu-\nate the performance of U-Net models trained with\nthe default atmos fwhm max = 0 .4 and variable\nsigma noise max ranging from 0 .01 to 1 .0. The\nmodels are then applied to validation images gen-\nerated with the default atmos fwhm max = 0.4 and\nwith a noise standard deviation distributed uni-\nformly 16 in the range [0 .05, 0.5].\nThe right plot of Figure 8 reveals that the U-Net\nmodel maintains robust performance only if trained\nwith noise levels equal to or higher than those of\nthe validation images (i.e., \xcf\x83 \xe2\x89\xa5 0.5). We notice\na sharp drop in performance with models trained\nwith \xcf\x83 < 0.5, especially at low observed SSIM.\nIt is noticeable that for the model trained with\n\xcf\x83 = 0.01, the outputs have the same SSIM as the\nobserved images, indicating a lack of deconvolution\npower.\nThese observations highlight both the robustness and\nthe limitations of the U-Net model, which is capable of\nadapting to varying seeing conditions. Concerning the\nnoise level, the test emphasizes the importance of train-\ning with noise conditions representative of the validation\nconditions.\n6. SUMMARY AND DISCUSSION\n6.1. Summary\nIn this work, we addressed thecore question introduced\nin Section 1.1: Can a U-Net architecture, originally de-\nsigned for image segmentation and denoising, perform\nend-to-end blind deconvolution of astronomical images\nwithout relying on hybrid pipelines or prior knowledge of\nthe Point Spread Function (PSF) and noise character-\nistics? To answer this question, we designed a compre-\nhensive experimental framework that simulates realistic\nastronomical observations using the GalSim toolkit, in-\ncluding random transformations, convolution with PSFs\naccounting for optical and atmospheric effects, and the\naddition of Gaussian white noise. We trained a U-Net\nmodel using a Mean Square Error (MSE) loss function\nand evaluated its performance as a function of the train-\ning dataset size and its ability to generalize under varying\nseeing conditions and noise levels.\n16 This is a bit different from Table 2 settings.\n10\n0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0\nSSIM obs.\n0.0\n0.2\n0.4\n0.6\n0.8\n1.0SSIM deconv.\nFWHM max for generation: 0.8\nFWHM max\ntraining\n0.1\n0.2\n0.4\n0.6\n0.8\n0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0\nSSIM obs.\n0.0\n0.2\n0.4\n0.6\n0.8\n1.0SSIM deconv.\nsigma max for generation: 0.5\nsigma max\ntraining\n0.01\n0.05\n0.10\n0.50\n1.00\nFig. 8.\xe2\x80\x94 Generalization performance of the U-Net blind deconvolution model. Left: SSIM of deconvolved images as a function of the\nSSIM of observed images, for validation images generated with a maximum FWHM of 0.8. The color gradient of the data points indicates\nthe maximum FWHM used during training, ranging from 0.1 (light blue) to 0.8 (red). Right: SSIM of deconvolved images as a function\nof the SSIM of observed images, for validation images generated with a noise standard deviation ( \xcf\x83) with a maximum value of 0.5 and\na minimum value of 0.05. The color gradient indicates the maximum \xcf\x83 used during training, ranging from 0.01 (light blue) to 1.0 (red).\nError bars indicate the standard error on the mean for each bin.\nOur results, presented in Sections 5.1, 5.2, and 5.3,\ndemonstrate that the U-Net model is quite effective in\ndeconvolving galaxy images, even under challenging con-\nditions. We observed that the model\xe2\x80\x99s performance im-\nproves consistently with an increasing number of training\nimages, with PSNR and SSIM metrics tending to sat-\nurate for training sets larger than 5 , 000 images. The\ncosine similarity analysis (Section 5.3) further revealed\nthat two independently trained U-Net models produce\nincreasingly similar outputs as the training set size in-\ncreases, suggesting convergence towards a stable solu-\ntion. Notably, the similarity continues to increase be-\nyond the 5 , 000 training size, indicating that the cosine\nsimilarity of the output models is a more sensitive metric,\nas previously explored in Campagne (2025).\nIn Section 5.4, we compared the performance of the U-\nNet model with the oracle-like Tikhonov non-blind de-\nconvolution method, which assumes perfect knowledge\nof the PSF and ground truth images. Surprisingly, the\nU-Net model not only matched the performance of the\nTikhonov method but also outperformed it in challeng-\ning conditions, particularly at low PSNR and medium\nSSIM values. This outcome directly addresses our core\nquestion by demonstrating that the U-Net architecture\ncan indeed perform end-to-end blind deconvolution effec-\ntively.\nFinally, in Section 5.5, we assessed the generalization\ncapability of the U-Net model under varying seeing con-\nditions and noise levels. Our results reveal that the\nmodel demonstrates a notable ability to adapt to unseen\nseeing conditions (FWHM), maintaining consistent per-\nformance even when the validation FWHM differs from\nthe training parameters. However, its robustness to noise\nvariations is more constrained: the model performs op-\ntimally only when trained with noise levels equal to or\nhigher than those encountered during validation. This\nhighlights both the flexibility of the U-Net architecture\nin handling atmospheric distortions and the critical im-\nportance of matching noise conditions between training\nand application scenarios.\n6.2. Discussion\nWhile hybrid methods combining traditional and deep\nlearning approaches have shown success in previous stud-\nies, such as in Sureau et al. (2020); Akhaury et al. (2024),\nthis work focuses on exploring the intrinsic capabilities of\na standalone U-Net model for end-to-end blind deconvo-\nlution in astronomical imaging. Although using a U-Net\nalone may not represent the current state-of-the-art, our\nresults highlight its remarkable potential in this context.\nThe ability of the U-Net model to generalize across vary-\ning conditions of seeing and noise, and to outperform\nthe oracle-like Tikhonov deconvolution in certain chal-\nlenging scenarios, provides a positive answer to our core\nquestion.\nThe findings of Kadkhodaie et al. (2024) provide a\nvaluable framework for interpreting our results. The\nauthors characterized the U-Net network as learning a\nform of geometry-adaptive harmonic basis during denois-\ning tasks, extending beyond traditional steerable wavelet\nbases. Although a rigorous mathematical analysis of the\nU-Net\xe2\x80\x99s behavior in end-to-end blind deconvolution is not\nyet available to our knowledge, our experiments with C \xce\xb1\nimages (Appendix C) suggest a similar mechanism. The\neigenvectors of the U-Net\xe2\x80\x99s Jacobian exhibit oscillating\npatterns, adapting to the geometry of the input image,\nand the decomposition in the eigenbasis is sparse. In clas-\nsical non-blind deconvolution (Section 2), sparse repre-\nsentations, particularly through multi-resolution wavelet\nanalysis, play a crucial role. If the U-Net is indeed learn-\ning such adaptive sparse representations during decon-\nvolution, it could explain its ability to effectively reveal\nthe ground truth image, warranting further theoretical\ninvestigation.\nHowever, some caveats must be acknowledged. While\nthe U-Net model demonstrates valable performance, its\neffectiveness is still influenced by the similarity between\ntraining and validation conditions. Although we em-\nployed a probabilistic forward model (Sections 4.1, 4.2),\nthe deconvolution performed by the U-Net is not en-\ntirely blind, as the training data implicitly encodes cer-\ntain characteristics of the PSF and noise distributions.\n11\nThis suggests that the network\xe2\x80\x99s ability to generalize is\ncontingent on the representativeness of the training data.\nFuture work could extend this study by employing\nlarger datasets composed of larger and more diverse and\nstructurally complex galaxy images. Additionally, ex-\nploring the transferability of these techniques to other\ndomains could provide further insights into what the\nnetwork learns during the image deconvolution process.\nSuch investigations may help confirm whether the U-\nNet\xe2\x80\x99s performance is domain-specific or indicative of a\nmore general capability to learn adaptive sparse repre-\nsentations as suggested by our experiments with C \xce\xb1 im-\nages. Another avenue would be to replace the classical\nU-Net architecture, which relies on convolutional kernels,\nwith more advanced variations such as those proposed in\nAkhaury et al. (2024).\nFinally, notice that, unlike the objective in Equa-\ntion 11, which aims to jointly estimate the Point Spread\nFunction (PSF) and the deconvolved image, our current\nU-Net architecture only outputs the deconvolved image,\nwithout providing explicit information about the blur-\nring kernel. This limitation opens a potential research\navenue to investigate whether the U-Net\xe2\x80\x99s learned sparse\nrepresentation could implicitly encode information about\nthe PSF.\nIn conclusion, this work demonstrates the potential of\nU-Net architectures for end-to-end blind deconvolution\nin galaxy imaging, particularly for small image patches.\nIt lays the groundwork for further research into the un-\nderlying mechanisms of the U-Net\xe2\x80\x99s deconvolution capa-\nbilities and opens avenues for exploring its applicability\nacross different imaging domains.\n7. REPRODUCIBLE RESEARCH\nThe companion repository on GitHub (https://github.\ncom/jecampagne/Blind-deconvolution-compagnon) con-\ntains all the codes for network training, data preprocess-\ning, and plot generation. The COSMOS Real Galaxy\nDataset, used for training and validation, is available\non Zenodo (https://zenodo.org/records/3242143). The\ncode is released under the MIT License, and the COS-\nMOS dataset is available under a CC-BY 4.0 license.\nLARGE LANGUAGE MODEL USE DISCLOSURE\nWe used Le Chat CNRS Enterprise, an AI-powered\nlanguage model developed by Mistral AI 17 and tailored\nto the research needs of the National Centre for Scientific\nResearch (CNRS), to assist in refining the clarity and\nfluency of the English text. All AI-generated suggestions\nwere carefully reviewed and validated by the author.\nACKNOWLEDGMENTS\nWe thank the French GENCI\xe2\x80\x93IDRIS for pro-\nviding access to Nvidia V100 resources under\nGrant 2025-AD010413957R2. Our code for pro-\ncessing galaxy images is inspired by the work\nof Li and Alexander (2023) and is available at\nhttps://github.com/Lukeli0425/Galaxy-Deconv/\nunder the MIT License. The code for han-\ndling C \xce\xb1 images is inspired by the work of\nKadkhodaie et al. (2024) and is available at\nhttps://github.com/LabForComputationalVision/\nmemorization generalization in diffusion models under\nthe MIT License.\nREFERENCES\nO. Ronneberger, P. Fischer, and T. Brox, in Medical Image\nComputing and Computer-Assisted Intervention \xe2\x80\x93 MICCAI\n2015, edited by N. Navab, J. Hornegger, W. M. Wells, and\nA. F. Frangi (Springer International Publishing, Cham, 2015)\npp. 234\xe2\x80\x93241.\nZ. Kadkhodaie, F. Guth, E. P. Simoncelli, and S. Mallat, in The\nTwelfth International Conference on Learning Representations\n(2024).\nS. Mallat, A Wavelet Tour of Signal Processing: The Sparse\nWay, 3rd ed. (Academic Press, San Diego, CA, USA, 2009).\nA. N. Tikhonov, Dokl. Akad. Nauk SSSR 153, 49 (1963).\nJ. L. Starck, E. Pantin, and F. Murtagh, Publications of the\nAstronomical Society of the Pacific 114, 1051 (2002).\nF. Sureau, A. Lechat, and J.-L. Starck, A&A 641, A67 (2020),\narXiv:1911.00443 [astro-ph.IM].\nZ. Zhuang, T. Li, H. Wang, and J. Sun, Int. J. Comput. Vision\n132, 319\xe2\x80\x93348 (2023).\nP. Satish, M. Srikantaswamy, and N. K. Ramaswamy, Traitement\ndu Signal 37, 527 (2020).\nM. Millon, K. Michalewicz, F. Dux, F. Courbin, and P. J.\nMarshall, The Astronomical Journal 168, 55 (2024).\nP. Magain, F. Courbin, and S. Sohy, The Astrophysical Journal\n494, 472 (1998).\nN. Cantale, F. Courbin, M. Tewes, P. Jablonka, and G. Meylan,\nA&A 589, A81 (2016), arXiv:1602.02167 [astro-ph.IM].\nA. Berdeu, A&A 688, A18 (2024), arXiv:2407.21548 [eess.SP].\nN. Singhal, A. Kadam, P. Kumar, H. Singh, A. Thakur, and\nPranay, Jordanian Journal of Computers and Information\nTechnology (JJCIT) 11, 211 (2025).\nK. H. Jin, M. T. McCann, E. Froustey, and M. Unser, IEEE\nTransactions on Image Processing 26, 4509 (2017).\n17 https://mistral.ai\nC. J. Schuler, M. Hirsch, S. Harmeling, and B. Sch\xc2\xa8 olkopf, IEEE\nTransactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence 38,\n1439 (2016).\nO. Kupyn, T. Martyniuk, J. Wu, and Z. Wang, in 2019\nIEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision\n(ICCV) (2019) pp. 8877\xe2\x80\x938886.\nS.-J. Cho, S.-W. Ji, J.-P. Hong, S.-W. Jung, and S.-J. Ko, in\n2021 IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer\nVision (ICCV) (2021) pp. 4621\xe2\x80\x934630.\nL. Guo, J. Yu, N. Zhang, and C. Xiao, Pattern Recognition ,\n112774 (2025).\nL. Xu, J. Ren, C. Liu, and J. Jia, Advances in Neural\nInformation Processing Systems 2, 1790 (2014), 28th Annual\nConference on Neural Information Processing Systems 2014,\nNIPS 2014 ; Conference date: 08-12-2014 Through 13-12-2014.\nF. Nammour, M. A. Schmitz, F. M. Ngol` e Mboula, J.-L. Starck,\nand J. N. Girard, Journal of Fourier Analysis and Applications\n27, 88 (2021).\nF. Nammour, U. Akhaury, J. N. Girard, F. Lanusse, F. Sureau,\nC. Ben Ali, and J.-L. Starck, A&A 663, A69 (2022),\narXiv:2203.07412 [astro-ph.IM].\nT. Li and E. Alexander, Monthly Notices of the Royal\nAstronomical Society: Letters 522, L31 (2023),\nhttps://academic.oup.com/mnrasl/article-\npdf/522/1/L31/54607594/slad032.pdf.\nU. Akhaury, P. Jablonka, J.-L. Starck, and F. Courbin, A&A\n688, A6 (2024), arXiv:2405.07842 [astro-ph.IM].\nC.-M. Fan, T.-J. Liu, and K.-H. Liu, in 2022 IEEE International\nSymposium on Circuits and Systems (ISCAS) (2022) pp.\n2333\xe2\x80\x932337.\n12\nA. Paszke, S. Gross, F. Massa, A. Lerer, J. Bradbury, G. Chanan,\nT. Killeen, Z. Lin, N. Gimelshein, L. Antiga, A. Desmaison,\nA. K\xc2\xa8 opf, E. Yang, Z. DeVito, M. Raison, A. Tejani,\nS. Chilamkurthy, B. Steiner, L. Fang, J. Bai, and S. Chintala,\n\xe2\x80\x9cPytorch: an imperative style, high-performance deep learning\nlibrary,\xe2\x80\x9d in Proceedings of the 33rd International Conference\non Neural Information Processing Systems (Curran Associates\nInc., Red Hook, NY, USA, 2019).\nD. P. Kingma and J. Ba, in 3rd International Conference on\nLearning Representations, ICLR 2015, San Diego, CA, USA,\nMay 7-9, 2015, Conference Track Proceedings , edited by\nY. Bengio and Y. LeCun (2015).\nB. Rowe, M. Jarvis, R. Mandelbaum, G. Bernstein, J. Bosch,\nM. Simet, J. Meyers, T. Kacprzak, R. Nakajima, J. Zuntz,\nH. Miyatake, J. Dietrich, R. Armstrong, P. Melchior, and\nM. Gill, Astronomy and Computing 10, 121 (2015).\nR. Mandelbaum, C. Lackner, A. Leauthaud, and B. Rowe,\n\xe2\x80\x9cCosmos real galaxy dataset,\xe2\x80\x9d (2012).\nJ.-E. Campagne, MNRAS 539, 3445 (2025),\nhttps://academic.oup.com/mnras/article-\npdf/539/4/3445/63039573/staf533.pdf.\nZ. Wang, A. Bovik, H. Sheikh, and E. Simoncelli, IEEE\nTransactions on Image Processing 13, 600 (2004)\nAPPENDIX\nA. GENERATOR PARAMETERS\nIn Sections 4.1, 4.2 the images provided for training, testing and validation phases are based on random distributions.\nThe Table 2 gives the details.\nTABLE 2\nRandom number distributions with their default values used to generate training, testing, and validation datasets. U(a, b)\ndenotes the uniform distribution over the interval [a, b] \xe2\x8a\x82 R, while U({a, b, . . .}) is the discrete uniform distribution over\nthe finite set {a, b, . . .}. N (\xc2\xb5, \xcf\x83) represents the normal distribution with mean \xc2\xb5 and standard deviation \xcf\x83.\nParameter Distribution Default value\nAtmospheric PSF\nFWHM of the Kolmogorov function\n(arcsec)\natmos fwhm max \xc3\x97 U(0, 1) 0 .4\nEllipticity magnitude of the shear atmos e \xc3\x97 U(1, 2) 0 .01\nShear position angle (radians) 2 \xcf\x80 \xc3\x97 N (0, 1)\nOptical PSF\nDefocusing N (0, sigma defocus) 0 .10\nAstigmatism (axes x & y) N (0, sigma opt psf) 0 .07\nComa (axes x & y) N (0, sigma opt psf) \xe2\x80\x9d\nSpherical aberration N (0, sigma opt psf) \xe2\x80\x9d\nTrefoil (axes x & y) N (0, sigma opt psf) \xe2\x80\x9d\nObscuration opt obs min + opt obs width \xc3\x97 U(0, 1) (0 .1, 0.4)\n\xce\xbb/D lam ov d min + lam ov d width \xc3\x97 U(0, 1) (0 .017, 0.007)\nImage galaxy parameters\nMagnitude of the shear pd f(x) = x; s.t. x \xe2\x88\x88 [min shear,max shear] (0 .01, 0.05)\nShear position angle (radians) 2 \xcf\x80 \xc3\x97 N (0, 1)\nMagnification U(1, 1.1)\nRotation angle (radians) U({0, \xcf\x80/2, \xcf\x80, 3\xcf\x80/2})\nOffset along x and y axes (pixel unit) U(\xe2\x88\x921, 1)\nStandard deviation of the Gaussian white\nnoise\nsigma noise max \xc3\x97 U(0, 1) 1.0\nB. EXTRA OPTICAL PSF EXAMPLES\nThe Figure 9 presents some examples of Point Spread Function generated with some telescope optical characteristics\ncomplementing the example shown in Section 4.2.\nC. U-NET BLIND DECONVOLUTION WITH C\xce\xb1 SYNTHETIC IMAGES\nThe question raised in the Section 6.2 on the possible geometrical interpretation of what is learned by the U-Net\nmay be addressed following the work by Kadkhodaie et al. (2024), considering geometric C \xce\xb1 images. These synthetic\nimages consist of a regular frontier between regular backgrounds, where the degree of regularity is controlled by the\nparameter \xce\xb1, see examples in Figure 10.\nWe conducted the following experiment. First, we generated datasets of more than 100 , 000 images of d = 128 \xc3\x97 128\n13\nFig. 9.\xe2\x80\x94 Example of optical PSFs (zoom \xc3\x973) obtained from galsim.OpticalPSF (see Section 4.2 for details).\n= 1\n = 2\n = 3\n = 4\n = 5\n1.0\n0.5\n0.0\n0.5\n1.0\nFig. 10.\xe2\x80\x94 Examples of C\xce\xb1 images with varying regularity. Note that within a single image, the regularity of the backgrounds matches\nthat of the frontier.\npixels, with pixel values adjusted to the range [ \xe2\x88\x921, 1] and with regularity ranging from \xce\xb1 = 1 to \xce\xb1 = 5. Then, for\neach \xce\xb1-dataset, we employed a U-Net architecture with an increased number of blocks (i.e., 4), which differs from the\ndefault configuration used in our main experiments, to better handle the larger image size according to Table 1 of\nKadkhodaie et al. (2024). Unlike Kadkhodaie et al. (2024), we use architectures with biases in both the BatchNorm\nand Convolutional layers18.\nThe models were trained using the same methodology as described in Section 4.1, employing forward modelling.\nHowever, in the context of the synthetic images considered here, we applied convolution using Gaussian blur kernels\nwith random Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) in the range [0 , 10] pixels. Note that kernels with FWHM\nvalues below 1 pixel are replaced by an identity kernel. The i.i.d. additive Gaussian noise had a standard deviation \xcf\x83\nrandomly sampled from the range [0 , 0.5]. An example of the deconvolution of a C 5 image is given in Figure 11.\nClean\n Blurred & Noisy\n Deconv.\n1.0\n0.5\n0.0\n0.5\n1.0\n2\n1\n0\n1\n2\n1.0\n0.5\n0.0\n0.5\n1.0\nFig. 11.\xe2\x80\x94 Left: A clean C5 image, Middle: The image convoluted with a Gaussian kernel of FWHM = 10 to which is added a Gaussian\nwhite noie of \xcf\x83 = 0.5. Right: The image blindly deconvoluted.\nOne of the key results in Kadkhodaie et al. (2024), where U-Net is used solely as a denoiser, is that the trained\nU-Net reaches the optimal denoiser PSNR, which asymptotically increases with a slope of \xce\xb1/(1 + \xce\xb1) as a function\nof the input PSNR. Along these lines, Figure 12 shows the deconvolved PSNR as a function of the input PSNR for\nU-Nets trained blindly as described above and tested on images that were not blurred but only corrupted by additive\nwhite Gaussian noise with \xcf\x83 such that the PSNR ranges from 0 to 30. We observe that the blind-deconvolving U-Net\nperforms as well as the optimal denoiser in a pure denoising use case. In the context of a deconvolution task, to our\nknowledge there is no equivalent of the asymptotically slope relation.\nAnother key result in Kadkhodaie et al. (2024) concerns the eigendecomposition of the Jacobian of the denoiser. We\nbriefly recall the key ideas. In the context of a bias-free architecture, one can write (for notational simplicity, y is the\nobserved noisy image, equivalent to xo used in Equation 1):\n\xcb\x86x(y) = D(y) = \xe2\x88\x87yD(y) y. (C1)\n18 The authors motivate the use of a bias-free architecture to\nsimplify interpretation but argue that the learned sparse represen- tation results remain unaffected by the inclusion of biases.\n14\n0 5 10 15 20 25 30\nInput PSNR\n0\n10\n20\n30\n40\n50Output PSNR\nno blur, noise [0.03, 1.00]\nC1 : 0.50\nC2 : 0.67\nC3 : 0.75\nC4 : 0.80\nC5 : 0.83\nFig. 12.\xe2\x80\x94 Inspired by Figure 4 of Kadkhodaie et al. (2024), this figure shows results for a U-Nets trained for end-to-end blind deconvolu-\ntion. PSNR of the U-Net output as a function of the input PSNR, for U-Nets tested on images corrupted solely by additive white Gaussian\nnoise with varying \xcf\x83 (i.e. no blurring). The dashed lines represent the theoretical asymptotic slopes of the optimal denoiser, \xce\xb1/(1 + \xce\xb1).\nLet (\xce\xbbk(y), ek(y))1\xe2\x89\xa4k\xe2\x89\xa4d denote the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of \xe2\x88\x87yD(y), which depend on the observed corrupted\nimage y. Projecting y onto the eigenvector basis leads to\n\xcb\x86x(y) =\nX\nk\n\xce\xbbk(y) \xe2\x9f\xa8y, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9 ek(y), (C2)\nwhere \xe2\x9f\xa8\xc2\xb7, \xc2\xb7\xe2\x9f\xa9 denotes the inner product. The denoiser can then be interpreted as performing shrinkage in an adaptive\nbasis, with \xce\xbbk(y) acting as a threshold, similar to denoising in a fixed basis Mallat (2009). Even if the U-Net we have\nused is not bias-free, we can apply the eigendecompostion as explained by Kadkhodaie et al. (2024).\nIn the context of the denoising-only task, Kadkhodaie et al. (2024) shows examples of eigenvectors ek(y) and\nobserves that the eigenvectors exhibit oscillating patterns both along the contours and in uniformly regular regions,\nthus adapting to the geometry of the input image. The authors refer to this as a geometry-adaptive harmonic basis .\nMoreover, the decomposition of y in the eigenbasis is sparse, with only a few \xe2\x9f\xa8y, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9 having significant values, and\nthe eigenvalues \xce\xbbk(y) decay rapidly, exploiting this sparsity. However, in the context of the deconvolution task, the\nvalidity of these properties is questionable.\nFigure 13 shows, in the top panel, the evolution of the scalar products \xe2\x9f\xa8y, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9 (Equation C2) and \xe2\x9f\xa8xt, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9,\nwhere xt is the true image, as well as the eigenvalues \xce\xbbk(y), all as a function of k. The bottom panel displays the\nfirst 20 eigenvectors. We observe that both key features\xe2\x80\x94sparsity, with only a few significant scalar products, and\nthe eigenvectors forming a geometry-adaptive harmonic basis\xe2\x80\x94are present when the U-Net is tested on a C 5-image\ncorrupted by a Gaussian kernel with a Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) of 10 pixels and additive white Gaussian\nnoise with \xcf\x83 = 0.5. Notably, along the frontier the oscillatory patterns exhibit a width consistent with the blur kernel\xe2\x80\x99s\nFWHM. These results have informed the discussion in Section 6.\n15\n0 2500 5000 7500 10000 12500 15000\nk\n10 5\n10 4\n10 3\n10 2\n10 1\n100\n101\n102\n. , ek(y)\nxt, ek\ny, ek\n 10 12\n10 10\n10 8\n10 6\n10 4\n10 2\n100\nk(y)\nWith blurring fwhm=10\nWith blurring fwhm=10\nFig. 13.\xe2\x80\x94 Inspired by Figures 3 and 4 of Kadkhodaie et al. (2024), this figure shows results for a U-Nets trained for end-to-end blind\ndeconvolution. T op: Evolution of the \xe2\x9f\xa8xt, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9 and \xe2\x9f\xa8y, ek(y)\xe2\x9f\xa9 coefficients as well as \xce\xbbk(y) as a function of k where xt is a C5-image and\ny the same image corrupted by a Gaussian kernel with a Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) of 10 pixels and additive white Gaussian\nnoise with \xcf\x83 = 0.5. Bottom: The first 20 eigenvectors ek(y).\nThis paper was built using the Open Journal of Astrophysics LATEX template. The OJA is a journal which provides\nfast and easy peer review for new papers in the astro-ph section of the arXiv, making the reviewing process simpler\nfor authors and referees alike. Learn more at http://astro.theoj.org.'
